<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<rfc ipr="none">
    <front>
        <title>Buschtrommel</title>
        <author initials='T.S.' surname='Sturm' fullname='Tobias'>
            <organization>Karlsruhe Institute of Technology</organization>
            <address>
                <email>Tobias.Sturm@student.kit.edu</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials='B.H.' surname='Halbrock' fullname='Benjamin'>
            <organization>Karlsruhe Institute of Technology</organization>
            <address>
                <email>benjamin.halbrock@student.kit.edu</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials='M.W.' surname='Winter' fullname='Moritz'>
            <organization>Karlsruhe Institute of Technology</organization>
            <address>
                <email>moritz.winter@student.kit.edu</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <date />
        <area>Applications</area>
        <workgroup>Telematics project 12/13, Group 1</workgroup>
        <abstract>
          <t>This document is a draft for the official specification of the Buschtrommel protocol. Buschtrommel is used to find and transfer files between clients in the same network domain without the need for a central server.</t>
        </abstract>
    </front>
    <middle>
        <section title="Introduction">
          <t>This document specifies the Buschtrommel protocol, which is used for ad-hoc file transfer between peers in the same network domain.</t>
            <t>This specificiation defines package formats and required client behavior to enable such file transfers between conforming, well-behaved clients.</t>
            <t>This document describes the mechanisms required for completion of the following tasks:
                <list style="symbols">
                    <t>peer and file announcement</t>
                    <t>file transfer</t>
                </list>
            </t>
            <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",  "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="High Level Overview">
          <t>
            Buschtrommel is focused on scenarios, where clients (a.k.a peers) do not share files for a long time. Files are announced in a short-termed fashion. Clients will not be connected for more than a few hours. The fast announcement of new clients and files is one of the main focuses.
          </t>
          <t>The protocol features can be roughly split into two groups:
                <list style="symbols">
                    <t>announcement of peers and files</t>
                    <t>file transfers</t>
                </list>
            </t>
            <t>
                Announcement features are implemented on top of UPD and multicast groups.
                File transfers uses TCP peer-to-peer connections.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="General Notes">
            <t>The Buschtrommel protocol extensively uses the magic number 0x71 (113 in decimal) to faciliate distinguishing Buschtrommel's messages from other protocols and applications.</t>
            <t>Throughout this document, commands are explained with diagrams. Command fields are identified with capital letters, e.g. LEN. The corresponding decimal values specify the number of octets reserved for the field. Hexadecimal numbers written as 0xXX have a size of one octet. All multi-octet values are expected to be in network byte order.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Peer and File Announcement via Group">
          <t>
            There are no mechanisms like file list requests, or hello messages. Every peer announces himself and all offered files from time to time with so-called announcement messages. These messages have a TTL.
            A client, has to join a defined multicast group, if he wants to announce his presence (including his files), or wants to receive other clients' announcement messages. A client SHOULD be in the multicast group as long as it is running.
            Conventially, this multicast group is:
			<list style="symbols">
				<t>239.255.0.113 for IPv4</t>
				<t>ff02::7171 for IPv6</t>
			</list>
			All announcement communication takes place over UDP on port 1113.
            </t>
			
            <t>
                Upon joining the group, the peer SHOULD send his first announement message to the group:
                <figure align='center'>
                    <artwork>
+------+------+------+----------+-----+----------+
| MAG  |  OP  |  LEN |   NAME   | TTL |  FILES   |
+------+------+------+----------+-----+----------+
| 0x71 | 0x0  |  13  |    23    |  7  | 0 - 8164 |
+------+------+------+----------+-----+----------+
//TODO check if total length still fits into UDP
                  </artwork>
                </figure>
                The LEN field specifies the length of the data in bytes that follows after the TTL field (unsigned integer ranging from 0 to 2^13-1). The maximum value for LEN is 8164.
                The NAME field MAY contains a human readable name of the client (represented in ASCII chars). The name can contain all ASCII chars from 32 to 126. Names, that are shorter than 23 characters can be truncated with ASCII ETX code (003). Clients without a human-readable name are accepted. If the Name field is used, the Client SHOULD NOT change it's name. Other peers MUST NOT use the name for peer identification, because the name is necessarily not unique in the network.
                The TTL field indicates the valid duration of all the information that are contained in the message. The TTL is to interpret as unsigned int, ranging from 0 to 2^6-1. The TTL in seconds results from the formula seconds = (TTL * 10). TTLs range from 0 - 1280 seconds.


                The FILES field contains no, one, or multiple triples of file information, as described as follows:
                <figure align='center'>
                    <artwork>
+-----------+------+--------------+
| FILE-HASH | SIZE | DISPLAY-NAME |
+-----------+------+--------------+
|    8      |  64  |   1 - 512    |
+-----------+------+--------------+
| ...
                    </artwork>
                  </figure>
                  FILE-HASH is the SHA-256 over the content of the file.
                  SIZE represents the number of bytes of the file.
                  DISPLAY-NAME is a human readable name for the file. It can contain out of the ASCII chars 32 to 126. Names can be truncated with the ASCII ETX code (003). Empty names are allowed and are represented woth the ETX code only.
                  After a truncated name or a name with the length of 512 chars, either the next file tripe begins, or the LEN and therefor the end of the message is reached.
                </t>
                                <t>
                                        Consider the following restrictions:
                                        <list>
                                        <t>Clients MAY include a folder structure in the display name. If clients do so, '/' (ASCII 057) MUST be used as path seperator.</t>
                                                <t>Clients MUST NOT send the very same announcement message over the group, before it's TTL(which is a minimum of 60 seconds) is near to expiring (which is 30 seconds).</t>
                                                <t>Clients SHOULD send announcement messages, as soon as they provide a new file.</t>
                                                <t>Clients SHOULD NOT send a single message per file, but accumulate whenever possible.</t>
                                                <t>Clients MAY send multiple announcement messages, containing disjunct file sets, if they need more than 8164 bytes to announce all files.</t>
                                                <t>Clients SHOULD send an announcement with TTL = 0 before going offline to signal, that the files won't be avaliable. Clients MUS NOT send an announcement with TTL = 0 for other purposes.</t>
                                                <t>Clients MUST use the UDP checksum header field</t>
                                                <t>Clients SHOULD ignore incoming UDP packages that do have an invalid checksum</t>
                                        </list>
                                </t>
        </section>
        
                <section title="Directed File Announcement">
					<t>
						Clients can request others to send file announcements via unicast:
					<figure align='center'>
						<artwork>
+------+------+
| MAG  |  OP  |
+------+------+
| 0x71 | 0x2  |
+------+------+
						</artwork>
					</figure>
					This is called a solicitation packet.
					</t>
                    <t>
                        Clients SHOULD react to all solicitation packets by sending a announcement packet to this client via unicast.
                        Clients SHOULD NOT send a direct announcement if a group announcement is outstanding in the near future. It SHOULD instead prepone its group announcement.
                    </t>
                    <t>The directed file announcements have the same format as group announcements.</t>                    
                </section>

                <section title="File Transfer">
        <t>
            When a peer requests a file from a single peer, it MUST open a TCP-Socket with a chosen port and send a FILEREQ message to a peer, that offers the file:
            <figure align='center'>
                <artwork>
+------+------+------+-------+------+------+
| MAG  |  OP  | HASH | PORT  |  OFF | LEN  |
+------+------+------+-------+------+------+
| 0x71 | 0x1  |   8  |  32   |  64  |  64  |
+------+------+------+-------+------+------+
                </artwork>
            </figure>
            HASH contains the SAH-256 hash of a file, that has been announced before. Clients SHOULD request only files, that are contained in a announcement message, that has not been expired.
            The PORT has to be a used by a fresh socket, that awaits an incoming TCP connection from the other peer. The socket MUST be attached to the same ip address, from witch the FILEREQ was sent.
            OFF indicates the offset, from which on the other peer should send from. It addresses the bytes inside the file.
            LEN indicates the number of bytes, that shall be sent. This field can be set to 0, if the peer requests all bytes from the given offset untill the end
        </t>
        <t>
                        If the receiving peer wants to continue an aborted file transfer, it sends a new FILEREQ, with OFF indicating the first byte, that has not been received.
                </t>
                <t>
            If a peer wants to request one file from multiple hosts, it sends multiple FILEREQ to these hosts. Each FILEREQ MUST contains a different port, different OFF and different LEN.
            The OFFs and LENs SHOULD describe a partition of the whole file.
        </t>
        <t>
            Upon receiving such a message, a peer (a.k.a host) SHOULD begin with the file transfer.
            The file transfer begins by opening the TCP connection on the desired port to the requester. AS soon as the TCP connection is established, the FILEREQ is replayed. The receiver MAY check if all information are correct to ensure, that the correct file and filesegment will be transmitted.
            The host sends all requested data via the TCP socket, that is used exclusively for the requested file and segment. As soon as all bytes are transmitted, the TCP connection MUST be closed by the sender and the receiver.
            A receiver SHOULD close the TCP connection, if more bytes than requested are received.
            If the TCP connection gets aborted the sender MUST NOT try to reconnect. The receiver MAY reestablish a new transfer via a new FILEREQ.
            The requester MAY assume, that the host is not avaliable, if he registers no incoming TCP connection on the desired port within 30 seconds.
        </t>
    </section>
</middle>

<back>
    <references>
        <reference anchor="refs.RFC768">
                <front>
                               <title>User Datagram Protocol</title>
                        <author initials="J." surname="Postel" fullname="Jon Postel">
                                <organization abbrev="ISI">USC/Information Sciences Institute</organization>
                        </author>
                        <date month="August" year="1980" />
                </front>
                <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="768" />
                <seriesInfo name="STD" value="6" />
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="refs.RFC793">
                <front>
                               <title>Transmission Control Protocol</title>
                        <author initials="J." surname="Postel" fullname="Jon Postel">
                                <organization abbrev="ISI">USC/Information Sciences Institute</organization>
                        </author>
                        <date month="September" year="1981" />
                </front>
                <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="793" />
                <seriesInfo name="STD" value="7" />
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="refs.RFC791">
                <front>
                               <title>Internet Protocol</title>
                        <author initials="J." surname="Postel" fullname="Jon Postel">
                                <organization abbrev="ISI">USC/Information Sciences Institute</organization>
                        </author>
                        <date month="September" year="1981" />
                </front>
                <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="791" />
                <seriesInfo name="STD" value="5" />
        </reference>
    </references>
        
        <section title="Glossar">
                <list>
					<t>Peer - a client in general </t>
					<t>Host - an client, which offers a file to others</t>
				</list>
        </section>
  </back>
</rfc>